David A. Kyle Papers
David A. Kyle Papers
1947-1974
Kyle, David A.
1.5 linear ft.
Memorabilia, subject files, and writings of the American science fiction fan, author, publisher, and co-founder of Gnome Press
149117
Biographical History
David A. Kyle (1919-2016) was an American author, science fiction short story writer, publisher and co-founder of Gnome Press. He also wrote under the name Kyle Ackerman (Ackerman was his middle name).
Born in Monticello, New York, Kyle's lifelong involvement with science fiction spans more than seven decades. Beginning as a fan in the early 1930s, he became a writer and illustrator for pulp magazines. Later he worked as publisher, anthologist, illustrator, book designer, editor, and literary agent. In 1947 he and Martin Greenberg co-founded Gnome Press, the imprint that pioneered the first hardcover editions of works by such authors as Isaac Asimov, Sir Arthur C. Clarke, and Robert Howard. Kyle's own works include the award-winning A Pictorial History of Science Fiction and The Illustrated Book of Science Fiction Ideas and Dreams as well as three novels set in the Lensman universe (originated by E.E. "Doc" Smith in 1934) and many articles for various fanzines. Kyle was also an Air Force Reserve officer (Lt. Col.), working as a reporter and writer on civil defense topics, and founded radio station WPDM in Potsdam, New York in 1955.
At the 1955 WorldCon he met Ruth Evalin Landis, another science fiction fan; the two married in 1957 and had a son and daughter.
He has received several honors, among them First Fandom's Science Fiction Hall of Fame; a special award from the British Science Fiction Association; and an award for Outstanding Achievement from The International Society of Science Fiction, Horror and Fantasy. He was included in Starlog's list of the "100 Most Important People in Science Fiction and Fantasy." Kyle chaired NyCon II, the 1956 WorldCon, and was the Guest of Honor at CONstellation, the 1983 WorldCon.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The David A. Kyle Papers consists of correspondence, memorabilia, subject files, and writings.
Correspondence consists of a single folder with a few postcards and brief notes. Correspondents include Keith Laumer and Jim Warren.
Memorabilia is also a single folder with just a few items. These include a brochure put out by Isaac Asimov's publisher regarding his first visit to England in 1974, and a clipping of a newspaper article on the movie 2001, in which Kyle is quoted.
Subject files are as arranged and labeled by Kyle. Much of it relates to his work as a reporter and public information officer for the U.S. Air Force Reserves; topics include psychological warfare, television, and the Apollo 16 mission, which launch Kyle attended. Also in this series are several folders of material related to Gnome Press, of which Kyle was a co-founder. This includes business items (e.g., brochures and catalogs), manuscripts (drafts of blurbs, book summaries, and so on), and production material (printer's proofs, etc.).
Writings contains some Air Force material, but mostly consists of drafts of short stories by Kyle. Almost all are heavily revised and edited; some include Kyle's own later opinions ("Not much worthwhile here"). There are also a few items by others, filed at the end. Many of the stories are numbered; this, with the last folder of "working papers #59 and #60", suggests that Kyle sequentially numbered all his writing projects.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each series, material is alphabetical by title or topic.
Related Material
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; Literature -- American Fiction; Kyle, David A.; Pohl, Frederik.; Apollo 11 (Spacecraft); Apollo 16 (Spacecraft); Gnome Press.; United States. -- Air Force -- Public relations.; United States. -- Air Force Reserve.; WPDM (Radio station: Potsdam, N.Y.); American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Civil defense -- New York (State); Novelists, American.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Science fiction, American.; Science fiction fans.; Book jackets.; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Illustrations (layout features); Manuscripts for publication.; Printers' proofs.; Authors.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1962; undated; includes postcard from Keith Laumer, note from Jim Warren, form letter from Shasta Press (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous, 1953; 1966,; 1969,; 1974; DD Form 93 (emergency contact information), "Who's Who" entry, publisher's brochure for Asimov's first visit to Britain, clipping (Box 1)
  - Flight: From the Pages of Encyclopedia Britannica 1768-1968 / R.R. Donnelley and Sons, Jan 1968; photo-book, on the occasion of EB's 200th anniversary (Oversize 1)
  - A Footprint on the Moon / R.R. Donnelley and Sons, 1969; Apollo 11 commemorative photo-book, oversize (Oversize 1)
- Subject files
  - Air reserve reporter, 1961-1964; topics include civil defense, home fallout shelters, recruitment, aeronautics, role of public information officer; formats include press releases from Air Force News Service, program bulletins, radio spots, fact sheets, transcription of speech by Major General William Yarborough, etc.; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Apollo 16 project, 1972; Kyle attended the launch; material includes official flight plan, press kit, clippings, press releases, etc.; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Armed Forces Day, 1956; Kyle was involved in planning local events; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Community relations of Air Force bases, 1948-1950; includes Air Force guidelines as well as several drafts of a report, possibly by Kyle (Box 1)
  - Gnome Press
    - Business records, publicity (brochures, letters, blurbs); correspondence with printers; etc. (Box 1)
    - Manuscripts, drafts for blurbs, jacket copy, book summaries, etc. (Box 2)
    - Production material, includes printer's proofs of title and half-title pages, a few illustrations, book jacket for C.L. Moore book, etc.; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Production material, printer's proofs of title pages, half-titles (Oversize 1)
  - Psychological warfare, 1953; Naval Reserve seminar; notes and draft of paper, possibly by Kyle, which may have been presented at the seminar (Box 2)
  - Television project, circa 1955; notes, drafts, etc. relating to Air Force project on the uses of television in connection with national defense; 2 folders (Box 2)
    See also Writings: Air Force: Television survey.
- Writings
  - Air Force work
    - Air Force Reserve radio spots, 1953; includes letters to various stations soliciting their participation (Box 2)
    - Handbook for Air Force public information officers in the field of television, circa 1955 (Box 2)
    - Television survey, circa 1955; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Base ten, 1966-1967; drafts (Box 2)
  - Be it ever so humble, 1950; draft (Box 2)
  - Beanball bugaboo, 1949; draft (Box 2)
  - Blood relations, draft (Box 2)
  - Corpse for sale, 1948; 1951; drafts (Box 2)
  - Count ten, drafts (Box 2)
  - Cupid wore a mustache, drafts (Box 2)
  - Damn you, Max (alt title: My love is blind), drafts (Box 2)
  - Death thumbs a ride, 1948; drafts (Box 2)
  - Devil planet jailbreak, draft, noted as "an early story" (Box 3)
  - The ferryman on the river, 1966-1967; drafts (Box 3)
  - Observation tower, 1949; drafts and two critiques by author Dorothy McCleary, for whose class the story was written (Box 3)
  - A pictorial history of science fiction, jacket for British edition (Oversize 1)
  - Some dreams come in packages, 1967-1970[?]; drafts (Box 3)
  - Ten-pin tycoon (alt title: Keyman Kegler), 1947 or 1948; co-written with James MacCreigh (pen name for Frederik Pohl); drafts (Box 3)
  - The tender trap, 1947 or 1948; "working papers"; includes notes, clippings, outlines, charts, several drafts (Box 3)
  - The third moon of Mars, 1967-1968; drafts, related clipping (Box 3)
  - Three to get buried, 1966; drafts (Box 3)
  - Too many heroes, 1948 or 1949; draft (Box 3)
  - Touchdown tyrant, drafts (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, "working papers #59 and #60"; fragment of essay about science fiction publishing (Box 3)
  - Writings by others
    - Greenberg, Martin / Dictionary of Science Fiction, compiled by Greenberg, edited by Kyle; original first draft manuscript, with words and definitions stapled to pages (Box 3)
    - Peeples, Samuel / Introduction to Dictionary of Science Fiction, draft (Box 3)
    - Pohl, Frederik / Keynote speech from Discon II, Aug 1974; carbon typescript (Box 3)